给可怜的瘸子赏点东西吧?
Anything for a poor cripple?
我奉拿撒勒人耶稣的名
In the name of Jesus of Nazareth,
叫你起来行走
rise up and walk.
神立耶稣为主 为弥赛亚了
God made Jesus Lord and Messiah.
让他们闭嘴
Silence them now.
啊! 彼得!
Aah! Peter!
约翰... 我们可能永远出不去了
John... We may never leave here.
彼拉多明天打算亲自造访神庙
Pilate will visit the temple on Pentecost.
波阿斯 这就是先知们所说的可憎之事
Boaz, this is the abomination the prophets talked about.
那我们下手的时间就到了
Then our time has come.
哥尼流!
Cornelius!
但愿你死得其所
I hope your cause is worth dying for.
愿你如此
I hope yours is.
有人发现马尔库斯·德鲁苏斯被杀害了
Marcus Drusus was found murdered.
我们在附近逮捕了一伙人
We've arrested a group of men in the area.
处决他们
Execute them.
把杀手交出来
Deliver the assassin to us.
他荣光之国的名字 是应当称颂的
Blessed be the name of his glorious kingdom
直到永永远远
forever and ever.
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第4集
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调: 影子
翻译: 飘飘行天下 鸟生鱼汤 波特妹子
翻译: 奥利奥 小黄不小黄
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
你的一个朋友杀了我的一个朋友
A friend of yours killed a friend of mine.
他是谁?
Who is he?
速速杀了我吧
Just finish it.
你们造下的孽
Others will pay the price
会有别人来付出代价
for the things that you've done.
只要一个名字 你就能让他们免于受苦
A single name from you could spare them.
难道这不就是你想要的?
Isn't this what you wanted?
生杀大权?
Power?
滋味如何?
How does it feel?
很好
Good.
权利的... 滋味... 很好
It... feels... good.
巡抚 我必须要向您表示我深切的不安
Governor, I must express our deep discomfort.
您当然有权
It is of course your right
为罗马人之死主持公道
to pursue justice for a Roman death,
但在神殿处决三个犹太人实在不是...
but the killing of three Jews at the temple is not...
打开它
Open it.
这是什么?
What is this?
被谋害的那位罗马军官
The Roman officer who was murdered.
我们也很震惊有人公然在神殿闹事
We are appalled that someone could do this at the temple.
那个杀手是冲我来的
The assassin came for me.
这种事不会再有第二次
There will be no repeat offense.
鉴于我们没抓到杀手本人
And seeing as we do not have the assassin himself,
十个犹太人会替他接受惩罚
10 Jews will be punished in his place.
惩罚?
Punished?
钉上十字架
Crucified.
今日
Today.
巡抚 我... 我...
Governor, I... I'm...
能用其它方式予以补偿吗?
Is there not some other form of reparation?
明日也如此
And tomorrow.
后日也如此 你明白了吗?
And the day after that. Do you understand?
持续多少日?
How many days?
每天钉死十个犹太人
10 Jews will be crucified every day
直到我抓到那个想杀我的人为止
until I have the man who tried to kill me.
快点... 往前走
Come on... move it.
快点... 动起来!
Come on... move!
他们不过是孩子 看看他们呀
They're just boys. Look at them.
他们究竟犯了什么错?
What have they done?
你们在保护一个杀人犯
You're shielding a murderer.
只要他未落网 就一天杀十个人
10 will die each day that he evades justice.
我们应该把审判耶稣的信徒
We should delay the trial of Jesus' followers
推迟到袭击彼拉多的杀手被抓到之后
until Pilate's assassin has been caught.
不行 亚那 神殿现在应该表现强硬
No, Annas. The temple has to be seen to be strong now.
我们需要速速审判他们好终止混乱的局面
We need a quick trial to end their disruption.
让我去对付那个瘸子乞丐
Leave the crippled beggar to me.
我会处理好的
I will deal with it.
那个杀手有消息了吗 流便?
What news of the assassin, Reuben?
我找遍了所有人...
I've been to everyone...
反动分子 煽动分子 走私犯 甚至土匪
Reactionaries, agitators, smugglers, even bandits.
没人知道是谁干的
No one knows who did it.
再去查
Go again.
施加更大压力
Press harder.
就这样...
So...
开始了
it's begun.
你是否悔改你的罪?
Do you repent your sins?
我悔改
I do.
你是否信耶稣基督 神的儿子?
Do you believe in Jesus Christ, the son of God,
他被钉在十字架上杀了 又在第三日复活
who died on the cross and rose again on the third day?
我信
I do.
我奉圣父 圣子
Then in the name of the father and of the son
圣灵的名 为你施洗
and of the Holy Spirit, I baptize you.
回到城里去 等我们来传道
Go back to the city and wait for word from us.
我们会在夜晚来临前为你找到居所
We'll find you a place to stay before night falls.
我也要去耶路撒冷
I'm going to Jerusalem, too.
什么?
What?
我要知道我父亲究竟发生了什么事
I need to know what's happening to my father.
玛雅 你为何不同她一起去呢?
Mary, why don't you go with her?
我们会负责这里
We'll manage here.
彼得是你的父亲?
Peter's your father?
我听说了他许多事
I've heard lots about him.
我叫司提反
I'm Stephen.
我是玛雅
Maya.
我能和你们一起去吗?
Can I join you?
我们为受痛之人祈祷 也为施痛之人祈祷
We pray for all who are in pain and all who cause pain.
我们祈祷拥有力量 即便在恐惧与哀痛之时
We pay for the strength to resist the urge to inhumanity
也可克制不仁的冲动
that we feel in times of fear and mourning.
我们祈祷拥有勇气 即便旁人需索
We pray for the courage to resist the calls to inhumanity
也可克制不仁的求告
that others may make upon us.
愿我们摆脱伤痛与恐惧
May we find relief from our hurt and fear.
愿我们即使深受苦痛
And may we not, in our pain,
仍能对他人之伤痛与恐惧保有同情
lose our empathy for the hurt and fear of others.
我们为受痛之人祈祷 也为施痛之人祈祷
We pray for all who are in pain and all who cause pain.
爸爸
Papa.
他的名字 还有他的藏身地点
His name and where to find him.
没事的
It's all right.
不要哭
Don't cry.
好孩子
Big girl.
放她走
Let her go.
然后... 我就告诉你
Then... I'll tell you.
约翰 我们要死在今天了
We're going to die today, John.
前进!
Forward!
长官
Sir.
杀手的名字是波阿斯
The assassin's name is Boaz.
但他逃走了
But he has fled.
哥尼流 你让我失望了
You disappoint me, Cornelius.
计划继续进行
Continue as before.
你可以退下了
You may go.
波阿斯是犹太人
Boaz is a Jew.
你应该把这个名字告诉该亚法
You should give his name to Caiaphas.
他的人由他来找会更合适
He's better placed to find one of his own.
你建议我向该亚法低声下气?
You suggest that I humble myself before Caiaphas?
克劳迪娅 罗马从不向下属求助
Rome does not beg favors of its subjects, Claudia.
梅莱克?
Melek?
站起来
Stand up.
拿撒勒人给了你多少钱
How much did the Nazarenes pay you
让你假装被治愈?
to pretend you were healed?
没人给我一分钱
No one paid me anything.
彼得这个人 打算毁掉神庙
This man Peter intends to destroy the temple.
帮我们阻止他
Help us to prevent that.
这麻烦交给你们了
Your problem now.
彼得 告诉我
Tell me, Peter.
彼得
Peter.
你父亲本来给你起名叫西门 对吗?
Your father named you Simon, did he not?
是的
He did.
但你叫"彼得"
And yet "Peter".
谁给你的这个名字?
Who gave you this name?
拿撒勒人耶稣基督
Jesus Christ of Nazareth.
彼得 难道你不尊重你的父亲吗?
Don't you honor your father, Peter?
我尊重他
I do.
但是明显比不上一个因为亵渎神明
But apparently less than you honor a man
煽动叛乱而被处死之人
put to death for blasphemy and sedition.
彼得是个绰号 是种爱称
Peter is a nickname, a term of endearment.
意思不过是"我的磐石"
It simply means "my rock."
你们看 岩石可以用来建造...
You see, a rock can be something to build with...
比如说一座新的神庙
a new temple, for instance.
或者被用作武器
or it can be a weapon.
投石器中的石块
A rock in a sling.
问题是 你是哪一种?
The question is, which are you?
告诉我们 你们奉谁的名声称治愈了那个跛脚的人?
Tell us, in whose name do you claim the cripple was healed?
你们众人
Let it be known to all of you
和以色列百姓都当知道
and to all of the people of Israel
他得痊愈
that he was healed
是因你们所钉十字架的
by the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth,
拿撒勒人耶稣基督的名!
whom you crucified!
你是说拿撒勒人本人治好了他
Do you say the Nazarene himself healed him,
而不是神?
not God?
我说他得痊愈 因神以耶稣基督的名
I say he was healed by God in the name of Jesus Christ,
也即神叫他从死里复活的那人!
whom God resurrected from death!
你这个骗子!
You're liars!
没有治愈 只有欺骗
There was no healing, only deception.
我们知道这个... 所谓的奇迹
We know that this... this miracle
不过是一出戏院里
was nothing more than theater
演员们的把戏
with actors playing roles
好粉饰他们那个死去的拿撒勒人
to falsely glorify their dead Nazarene.
你是梅莱克 那个乞丐
You're the beggar known as Melek.
我是...
I am...
你自儿时便来神庙乞讨
And you beg to the temple since childhood,
那时就是瘸了的样子 对吗?
presenting yourself as lame, yes?
是的
Yes.
然而今天 在神面前
Yet today, in sight of God,
我们清楚地看到你腿脚很好
we clearly see you're quite well.
因为他从没瘸过
Because he was never lame.
他只是发现如果装成残疾的孩子
He'd simply found that appearing to be a sickly child
会更容易撬开路人的钱包 对吗?
was a more effective lever into a stranger's purse, yes?
实话实说 在神的眼下
Truthfully, under the eyes of God,
你是否承认这些人跟你合谋
do you admit these men conspired with you
制造出了被治愈的假象
to create the illusion of healing,
装出了他们所谓的奇迹?
a pretense which they claimed to be a miracle?
我是个穷人
I am a poor man.
我的一生都在这里乞讨
My whole life has been spent begging here.
我受过神庙的恩惠
And I'm beholden to this temple.
在神的眼下 我愿意说出实话
Under the eyes of God, I will tell the truth.
我生来双腿残疾
I was born lame.
一生中从没走过一步路
I never walked a step in my life.
没有把戏 没有欺骗
There was no trickery, no deception.
为了彼得 我赞美神
I praise God for this man, Peter,
赞美他们称为拿撒勒人耶稣的那个人
and the one they call Jesus of Nazareth.
我赞美神将我治愈
I praise God for healing me.
- 他们是无辜的 把他们放了  - 放了他们!
- They're innocent. Just release them.  - Free them!
放他们走!
Let them go!
放了他们!
Free them!
那么 那个跛子确实被治愈了
So, the cripple was healed.
该亚法 你现在是形势所迫
Caiaphas, your hand is forced.
你们将会被释放
You are to be released.
但是有前提条件的
But it is on the condition
你们不可奉拿撒勒人耶稣的名
that you do not speak or teach the name
讲论 教训人
of Jesus of Nazareth.
毁掉这个条件...
Break this condition...
那么反过来 我们就毁掉你们
and you, in turn, will be broken.
你已经审判了我们
You've judged us.
现在你们自己酌量吧 听从你们
Now you must judge, if in God's eyes,
不听从神 这在神面前合理不合理
it's right that we obey you rather than him.
趁我没改主意 赶紧从我眼前消失
Get out of my sight before I change my mind.
兄弟
Brother.
这么多人... 发生什么事了?
All these people... what happened?
都是你的功劳 而且还会有更多人来
You did. And they just keep coming.
西门
Simon.
你当时是准备要死了吗?
Were you prepared to die?
是的
Yes.
如果能有如此结果 那我愿再做一次
And if this is the result, I'm prepared to do it again.
朋友们 当初我离开之时
My friends, when I left here,
我们只有屈指可数的几个人而已...
there was little more than a handful of us...
东躲西藏
hiding.
担惊受怕
Timid.
焦急等待
Waiting.
但我今日回来 看到我们已经不计其数!
But now I return to find we are already beyond counting!
我们因信仰找到了彼此
We have found each other in faith,
我们必须以此为耀
and now we must honor that.
我们必须互相扶持
We must provide for each other
因为我们彼此互相汲取着力量
as we draw strength from each other.
你身边的人能够站稳
The man beside you stands
是因为有你的支持
because you are there to hold him up.
只要我们每个人都付出所有的 只索取需要的
We are united when each of us gives what we have
我们就是同心一体的
and takes only what we need.
神的国将要来临 而我们会有资格进入!
The kingdom of God is coming, and we will be fit to enter!
我的捐项
My offering.
有些人都给不了什么
Some have so little to give.
但他们愿倾其所有
But they give all they have,
那他们就是我们最大的恩主
and they're our greatest benefactors.
你确定吗? 你真的愿意把所有的都献出来?
Are you sure? Are you certain you want to give everything?
已经说好的
Well, that's the deal.
如果他们说的是真的
And if what they say is true,
神的国将要来临...
that the kingdom of God is coming...
是的 如果... 如果是真的
Yes, if... if it's true.
但如果属实 难道你不想成为其中一员
But if it's true, don't you want to be part of it
远离外界的一切朽坏与暴虐吗?
and away from all the corruption and misery out there?
原谅我 我是想相信
Forgive me. I want to believe.
真的想
I truly do.
我只是觉得我们应该谨慎些
I just think we should try to be cautious.
没错
Yes.
我们卖掉旧房子好在这里安个新家
We sold our old home for a new home here.
我们在世上所有的一切...
All that we have in the world...
我们都给他
we give to him.
- 你是彼得吗?  - 是的
- Are you Peter?  - I am.
请跟我来
Please, come.
我的女儿病了
My daughter's sick.
如果你愿意 请把她带回来
If you're willing, bring her back, please.
那将是神的旨意... 不是我的
It'll be God's will... not mine.
奉...
In the name...
奉耶稣基督的名 痊愈吧
In the name of Jesus Christ, be healed.
孩子 听我说
Child, hear me.
我与他同行 同吃 称他为我的朋友
I walked with him, ate with him, called him my friend.
奉耶稣基督的名 痊愈吧
In the name of Jesus Christ, be healed.
哦 谢谢你
Oh, thank you.
彼得 那真是...
Peter, that was...
我是说 我们得告诉大家这件事
I mean, we need to tell people about this.
我们应该到神殿去
We should go to the temple.
不 我们还不能去神殿传福音
No. We're not preaching in the temple yet.
但现在神与你同在
But God is with you right now.
我们得给大祭司看到这一切
We need to show the high priests.
我说了不行
I said no.
耐心点 司提反
Be patient, Stephen.
时机会到的
The time will come.
这些年轻人做了什么?
What have these young men done?
闪开 孩子
Move aside, boy.
这是巡抚的事
This is the Governor's business.
我问你他们做了什么要受此惩罚
I ask what they've done to deserve this.
闪开
Move aside.
不
No.
别逼我割了你的喉咙
Don't make me cut your throat.
我想留你一条小命
I want you to live.
为什么?
Why?
因为我宽宏大量
Because I am merciful.
都散开
Move along.
让出路来!
Clear the way there!
彼得
Peter.
告诉我你有什么困扰
Tell me what's troubling you.
一切都变化得太快了
Everything's changing so quickly.
你早知这条路不好走
You knew this wasn't going to be easy.
坏事将会发生...
Bad things are gonna happen...
在我身上...
to me...
在大家身上
The others.
可怕的事情
Terrible things.
我儿子选择你是有原因的
My son chose you for a reason.
他知道你的信仰足够强大
He knew your faith was strong enough
可以担当重任
to bear the responsibility,
可以帮你成为大家需要的人
to help you to become the man our people need you to be.
把他们带过来
Get them up there.
- 快点  - 是 长官
- Move it.  - Yes, sir.
彼拉多
Pilate.
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
你见过马库斯·德鲁苏斯吗?
Did you ever meet Marcus Drusus?
这就是他
Here he is.
被人杀害
Murdered.
要知道他们是冲我来的
They came for me, you know.
但现在我要用他们的骨灰堆积成山
But now I'm building a mountain of their ashes.
要是我能找得到你 他们也会的
If I've found you, they will find you.
但他们下手不会像我这么干脆利落
But they won't kill you quickly, like I would.
我不会招供的 利未 我发誓
I wouldn't tell them anything, Levi, I swear it.
但我不想冒这个风险
But I don't want that to be put to the test.
你若当真想杀我
If you were going to kill me,
之前在街上就下手了
you would have done it in the street.
为何没有?
So why not?
因为你杀了一个罗马人
Because you took a Roman life.
只要他们杀不了你
As long as they don't take yours,
你就能鼓舞众人
you're an inspiration.
你做得到 别人也做得到
If one can do it, so can others.
那你有何建议?
And what do you propose?
你就此销声匿迹
That you disappear.
你非等闲之辈 约翰
You're a very unusual man, John.
你认识我?
You know me?
我目睹了你的审判
I saw your trial.
就眼下而言 大多数人
Now, these days, most people,
因害怕钉十字架而低调行事
they keep a low profile for fear of crucifixion,
而你却...
and yet you...
我做了个梦
I had a vision.
它指引我来到这块开裂的石砖前
And it bids me to be here on this cracked stone.
这个...
Well...
听听没坏处
For what it's worth, um,
我不建议你现在就在这传福音
I would encourage against preaching here just yet.
我看得出你是个富贵之人
I see you're a man who's prospered.
如果我们保持沉默 你觉得满意吗?
Does it suit you if we stay quiet?
你臆断贵贱有别 真让我失望
I'm disappointed you assume my wealth sets us apart.
我很乐意倾尽所有
I would gladly exchange my last penny
来让你在这祭坛前向世人布道
to hear your message preached to the world from this altar.
- 那你为何没有?  - 只因为你没要求
- Then why don't you?  - You haven't asked.
你们把自己局限在贫苦之人中
You confine yourselves to the poor and sick.
而我有着同样贫苦的...
I'm poor and sick...
灵魂
in my soul.
我穷尽一生收集财富
I spent my life collecting wealth
到头来却被其占据一切
only to find it's taken my place.
只留下空虚的皮囊
The man is meaningless.
那就随我来吧... 就现在
Then come with me... now.
奉耶稣基督的名加入我们
Join us in the name of Jesus Christ,
你的内心就会富足起来
and the man will be fulfilled.
那你的梦呢?
What about your vision?
我相信是他引导我到这里找到你
I believe he led me here to find you.
当初同我来这的男人
The man I came here with
是一个可靠而有志气的外交官
was a dependable, ambitious diplomat.
但你却用大量的鲜血牺牲
But you are extracting a mass blood sacrifice
来平息你的震怒
to appease your almighty wrath.
你是怎么了?
What's happening to you?
我是罗马的权利工具
I am an instrument of Roman power.
我的行为便是那权利的体现和警示
My actions are an expression and a reminder of that power.
恰是这权利维系着罗马的统治
And that power sustains Rome.
至高无上的权利
It is paramount.
你永永远远不要插手
You will never, ever involve yourself
你不可能理解的事情
in what you plainly do not understand.
其实关于这块地有个小故事 呃
You know, there's a story, and, uh,
也许不过是卖家抬高地价的手段而已
it's probably no more than a means to inflate the price,
但我买下这块地皮的时候
but when I bought this land,
卖家向我保证大卫王曾在这扎营
I was assured King David once made camp here.
这是你买它的原因吗?
Is that why you bought it?
不 我买它只是为了赚钱
No. I bought it to make a profit.
花了一大笔钱
Paid through the nose.
很高兴现在送给了你们
Glad to give you this land.
巴拿巴...
Barnabas...
再好不过了
It's perfect.
一个新的开始
A new beginning.
我妹妹的独子...
My sister's only child...
我亲手抱过 教导过 爱过的孩子
A boy I... I cradled, taught, and loved,
此刻正被钉在十字架上
is at this moment hanging from a cross,
为不属于他的罪赎过!
paying a debt that was never his!
亲爱的朋友 我心都碎了 过来
Dear friend, I am heartbroken. Come.
- 约瑟  - 我不想听你那套陈词滥调
- Joseph.  - I don't want your platitudes.
我想要的 我们需要的 是结束这一切!
What I want and what we need is for this to end!
你靠着攀附彼拉多才到今天的地位
You've made a career out of being close to Pilate.
现在该是表现的时候了
Make it count for something now.
哪都不安全
Nowhere's safe.
有个地方
There is somewhere.
那里的人能宽恕我的罪过
There are people who can forgive my sins.
他们会找到你的
T... they'll find you.
求求你 留在这 陪着我
Please, stay here. Stay with me.
我不能
I can't.
他们会连你也杀了的
They'll kill you, too.
让他们杀吧
Then let them.
彼得
Peter.
你若能过来便是我们的荣幸
We'd be honored if you'd join us.
我能说 我们对你取得的成就敬佩不已吗 彼得?
May I say, we're in awe of what you've achieved here, Peter?
这个营地 所有的这些人
This camp, all these people,
他们到此只因为听了你的讲论
they're only here because they heard you speak,
我们也是
ourselves included.
这一切都不能归功于我
None of this is my achievement.
而是拜圣灵所赐
It's the work of the Holy Spirit.
我们在它的面前感到卑微
And we're humbled in its presence.
神啊 我向您大声求告
I cry aloud, aloud to God,
向神求告 请您应允我
aloud to God that he may hear me.
我从没见他这样过
I've never seen him like this.
你丈夫的虔诚可嘉
Your husband's devotion is admirable.
我在患难之日求主
In the day of my trouble, I seek the Lord.
他在神前忘我和谦卑来寻求宽慰
He takes comfort in forgetting and humbling himself before God.
我的灵魂无法得到慰藉
My soul refuses to be comforted.
这样看来 你我都是懦夫
In which case, we're all cowards.
不 他所拥有的地位和责任
No, he has a position and a responsibility
我们都没有
that none of us have.
你叫我不能闭眼
You hold my eyelids from closing.
我烦乱不安 无法言语
I am so troubled that I cannot speak.
神啊 我向您大声求告 向神求告 请您应允我
I cry aloud to God, aloud to God that he may hear me.
我在患难之日求主
In the day of my trouble, I seek the Lord.
波阿斯
Boaz.
我们是要像男人一样好好说话
Shall we talk like men,
还是要像小孩子一样争吵?
or shall we squabble like children?
我们已经谈过了
You and I have already spoken.
如果还是无法达成一致的话 这就不是你该待的地方
If we're still at odds, then this place is not for you.
那我怕我们就要开吵了
Then I fear we are about to squabble.
我不会评判你 我也不知道你为什么在这里
I don't judge you, and I do not know why you're here.
我只知道你所相信的行事方法
I only know that you believe in a course of action
是我不会容忍或宽恕的
that I will not tolerate or condone.
但是如果你想要对耶稣
But if you're willing to repent your sins
悔改你的罪...
in the name of Jesus...
我是相信神的人
I am a man of God,
但是我在经上却没有看过
but I do not recognize this name Jesus
耶稣的名字
from the scriptures.
我记得有约书亚 所罗门 大卫王... 都是战士
I recall Joshua, Solomon, King David... all warriors.
你已经迷失在仇恨中了吗?
Are you so lost to hate?
你记得诗篇吗 彼得?
Do you recall the psalms, Peter?
"耶和华我的磐石 是应当称颂的 他教导我的手争战"
"Blessed be the Lord, my rock, who trains my hands for war."
这里有人在利用我们
There are people here who take advantage of us.
那就指名出来 我们会保证他们离开这里
Then name them, and we'll see to it that they leave.
不行
No.
这不是我们做事的方法
It's not the way.
那该做什么?
Then what's to be done?
我们在世上所有的一切 我们都给他
All that we have in the world, we give to him.
你还好吗?
Are you feeling all right?
亚拿尼亚 你的心里有什么
What's in your heart, Ananias,
叫你欺哄圣灵?
to make you lie to the Holy Spirit?
- 什么?  - 你把房子的价银
- What?  - You've kept for yourself
给自己私自留下了一些
some of the money from the sale of your house.
你怎么心里起这意念呢?!
What made you think of doing such a thing?!
无稽之谈
This is absurd.
你欺哄人
You've lied.
不光是欺哄我们 是欺哄神了
Not just to us, but to God.
把他埋了
Bury him.
快去
Now.
彼得
Peter.
发生什么事了?
What's happened?
亚拿尼亚在哪里?
Where's Ananias?
撒非喇
Sapphira.
请你 实话实说
Please, speak truthfully.
你和你的丈夫把房子卖掉的时候
When you and your husband sold your house,
有没有给自己私自留下一些?
did you keep anything back for yourselves?
我们没有
We did not.
你在说谎
You're lying.
我知道你们自己留了一点
I know you held it back.
圣灵告诉我的
The Holy Spirit told me so.
可能是留了一点 那又有什么关系?
There may have been something, but what does that matter?
我们捐献了很多钱 也乐意如此
We donated a huge amount, and happily so.
这当然有关系 因为你否定了我们的事会成功!
It matters because you bet against our mission succeeding!
你是在否定神啊 撒非喇!
You bet against God, Sapphira!
你们为什么同心试探主的灵呢?
How can you conspire to test the spirit of the Lord?!
这绝无恶意!
It was not malicious in any way!
我们不过是想谨慎一点!
We were simply being prudent!
亚拿尼亚在哪里?
Where's Ananias?
你听
Listen.
埋葬你丈夫之人的脚
The feet of the men that buried your husband
已到门口
are just outside.
他们也要把你埋葬
And they mean to bury you, too.
巡抚
Governor.
我来是求你发发慈悲
I come to ask for mercy.
求你了 不要再把人钉上十字架了
Please, let the crucifixions end.
呃 我不明白了
Uh, I don't understand.
你被攻击了吗?
Were you attacked?
这是我们致哀的一种形式
It is ritual to mark our grief.
致哀?
Your grief?
我可以畅所欲言吗?
May I speak freely?
这无益于你的形象
It doesn't look good for you.
是吗? 怎么说?
Really? How so?
你作为巡抚的首要职责
Your chief responsibility as Governor
是维持和平 但你却没有担起职责
is to maintain the peace, but you squandered that.
由于你的所作所为
Because of your actions,
城里弥漫着反对罗马的情绪
anti-Roman feeling fills the city.
会有更多的流血事件
More blood will be spilled.
罗马人的血
Roman blood.
你有一千人
You have a thousand men.
我们有一百万
We have a million.
你 彼拉多 由于你灾难性的误判
You, Pilate, will have provoked insurrection
激起了暴乱
through your catastrophic misjudgment,
你 彼拉多 将就此终结
and you, Pilate, will be finished.
抓住他
Restrain him.
张开你的嘴
Open your mouth.
吃了
Eat.
不
No.
吃了它
Eat it.
不
No.
我叫你吃了它
I said eat it.
我想做什么就做什么 直到我达成目的为止!
I will continue as I see fit until I have what I want!
绝不手下留情!
There will be no mercy!
利亚
Leah.
彼拉多这种暴行是找不到杀手的 但是你可以
Pilate's brutality will never find the assassin, but you can.
你能让这一切结束
You can end this.
他的名字叫波阿斯
His name is Boaz.
你取了一个人的性命 你是个杀人犯
You've taken a man's life. You're a killer.
有多少犹太人的命落在了罗马人手里?
How many Jewish lives have fallen to the Romans?
我们不能眼睁睁看着兄弟姊妹们受苦!
We cannot watch our brothers and sisters suffer!
只有神能决定谁生谁死
Only God decides who lives and dies.
别考验我的耐心!
Do not test me!
逮捕他们 你会被处死
Arrest them. You're to be put to death.
那就来吧
So be it.
就现在!
Now!
伟大的改变即将来临
The great change is coming.